Guide to the Charles Butterworth Papers 1856-1975
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
Charles Butterworth papers
1856-1975
1893-1970
Oregon Historical Society, Davies Family Research Library Research Library 1200 SW Park Avenue Portland, Oregon 97205 Phone: 503-306-5240 Fax: 503-219-2040 E-mail: libreference@ohs.org
Mss 2427
Charles Butterworth, 1858-1936.
1 cubic foot (2 document cases, 1 flat box)
Papers of a photographer and painter of Portland, Oregon, including studio log books, genealogical materials, writings, and a small amount of correspondence. Also included is correspondence of Charles Butterworth's daughter Esther; and minutes of the Trails Club of Oregon, 1928-1930.
Biography of Charles Butterworth:
Photographer and painter Charles Butterworth was born in 1858 in Mainsville, near Cincinnati, Ohio. He grew up on his parents' farm and went to New Vienna, Ohio, to study photography. There he married Etta Miller in 1883. He worked as a photographer in Wilmington, Ohio, then moved with his family to Ontario, California, in 1895. In 1898 the Butterworths relocated to Portland, Oregon, where they remained the rest of their lives. Charles Butterworth achieved recognition for his artistic photographic work, especially children's portraiture, and he was instrumental in the formation of the Photographic Association of Portland. The Butterworths had two children, Arthur and Esther. Esther Butterworth (1889-1975) became a photographer herself, and was also known as a photo colorist. She worked for a time in the studios of photographer Edwin S. Curtis in Los Angeles.
The collection includes a small amount of correspondence of Charles and Etta Butterworth, writings of Charles Butterworth, genealogical materials, minutes of The Trails Club, and correspondence of Esther Butterworth. Also included are Charles Butterworth's studio log books dating from 1911-1933 (with gaps). Of special interest among the correspondence is a letter from Charles Butterworth, 1893, describing the World's Columbian Exposition in Chicago; and a letter from Etta Butterworth describing the family's train trip from Ohio to California in 1895.
The collection is arranged in two series:
Series A: Charles Butterworth papers, 1856-1970
Series B: Esther Butterworth papers, 1862-1975
The collection is open to the public.
Gift of David L. Davies, 1976 August; and Russel I. Butterworth, 1976.
Charles Butterworth's painting of Ezra Meeker is housed in the Artifact Collections, Oregon Historical Society.
The collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings:
Butterworth, Charles, 1858-1936.; Butterworth, Esther.; Butterworth, Etta Miller.
Trails Club of Oregon--Archives.; World's Columbian Exposition (1893: Chicago, Ill.)
Butterworth family.
Portland (Or.)--History.; United States--Description and travel--1865-1900.
Clubs--Oregon--History.; Photographers--Oregon--Portland--History.; Photography--Oregon--Portland--History.
Oregon; Portland
Letters (correspondence); Logs (records)
Photographer.
- Charles Butterworth papers, 1856-1970; Series A
  - Correspondence
    - 1893-1899 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - 1908-1918 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - 1921-1936 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Fragments and undated letters (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Butterworth genealogical materials, 1856-1970 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Writings of Charles Butterworth, undated (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Marriage certificate and wedding invitation, 1883 (Box-folder 1/7)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1883-1936 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - Pacific International Photographers Association, certificate of membership, undated (Box-folder 1/9)
    - Trails Club of Oregon minutes, 1928-1930 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Photography studio logs
    - Studio journal, 1911-1916 (Box-folder 3/1)
    - Studio register, 1911 June-1915 April (Box-folder 3/2)
    - Studio register, 1919 October-1920 November (Box-folder 3/3)
    - Studio register (with date gaps), 1920-1933 (Box-folder 3/4)
    - Studio register--Loose pages from above book, 1920-1933 (Box-folder 3/5)
    - Studio register, 1925 December-1931 January (Box-folder 3/6)
- Esther Butterworth papers, 1862-1975; Series B
  - Photographs of ancestral sites, circa 1960-1970 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Family poems, undated (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Sesquicentennial scrapbook, Religious Society of Friends, 1970 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - "My family genealogy" (ledger book), undated (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Correspondence, 1932-1975 (Box-folder 2/1-2)
  - Documents and ephemera, 1862-1970 (Box-folder 2/3)